MAARIJ TAHIR

maarijtahir1@gmail.con +1 (646) 659-8296 linkedin.com/in/maarijtahir

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Seasoned Software Engineer with 5 years of professional experience, proficient in web server-side languages and frameworks. Experienced in Data Engineering and Natural Language Processing fundamentals. Expert in all stages of the software lifecycle with a firm grasp of Object-Oriented and Functional Programming principles.

EDUCATION

Cornell University, College of Engineering, Ithaca, New York

Aug 2016 - May 2017

MEng. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.4

Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS), Lahore, Pakistan

Aug 2012 - May 2016

B.S. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.65 (High Merit)

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer III, Expedia Group (Flights)

Sept 2018 - Present

- Designed and built the Compare & Upgrade Fares feature for the Flights Search Page that touched numerous micro-services to help 30 million monthly visitors compare fares more conveniently. Led directly to a 6.5% increase in fare upgrades.
- Spearheaded the development of core features from business requirements for the freshly minted Flights Progressive Web App using GraphQL and Kotlin.
- Designed post-booking functionality like Flight Cancellation and Credit Redemption from the ground up leading to a 60% decrease in customer propensity to call a live agent.
- Collaborated to migrate data in SQL databases to MongoDB collections and reduced the Web App response time by 28%.
- Increased Web App resiliency by setting up a separate new environment to perform automated Perf and Chaos testing.
- Applied AWS knowledge to migrate microservices to dedicated segments in the AWS cloud.
- Mentored new hires and facilitated agile development by decomposing major deliverables into simpler tasks through extensive research and meticulous planning.

Software Engineer I, Expedia Group (Partner Revenue Management)

Feb 2018 - Sept 2018

- Designed and implemented the process of productionalizing predictive data science models using Spark (in Scala) and Hive that provided insights to over 60,000 hotel chains around the world.
- Created an ETL pipeline using Spark, Qubole and Jenkins to pull, sanitize and transform Terabytes of data from our partners into information that helped them achieve highly competitive hotel room pricing.
- Utilized Java Spring, Node.js and MongoDB to design new WebApp features that increased Monthly Active Users by 5.2% YoY for 4 consecutive months.
- Leveraged knowledge in AWS services like ECS, S3, SQS, CloudFormation and Lambda.

Software Developer, Royal Cyber (Software Services)

Aug 2017 - Jan 2017

- Built a ChatBot solution that created and maintained dialogue with users and automated user query resolution.
- Created a scalable RESTful API-oriented backend using Node.js, Express and MongoDB that supported multiple user channels like Facebook, Website Chat and SMS effectively and concurrently.
- Gained expertise in conversational frameworks like Google DialogFlow and Amazon Lex.
- Presented as one of the company's most promising upcoming products at the conference Shop.org held in Los Angeles, CA.

SPECIALIZED SKILLS AND LANGUAGES

Programming Languages: Java, Scala, Kotlin, JavaScript **Backend Frameworks**: Spring, GraphQL, Camel, Node.js

Storage Systems: SQL, MongoDB, Redis, Spark, Hive

Miscellaneous: Jenkins, Git, Perforce, Chef, Docker